Tonight, I want to have a conversation about this incredible global issue that's at the intersection of land use, food and environment, something we can all relate to, and what I've been calling the other inconvenient truth. But first, I want to take you on a little journey. Let's first visit our planet, but at night, and from space. This is what our planet looks like from outer space at nighttime, if you were to take a satellite and travel around the planet. And the thing you would notice first, of course, is how dominant the human presence on our planet is. We see cities, we see oil fields, you can even make out fishing fleets in the sea, that we are dominating much of our planet, and mostly through the use of energy that we see here at night. But let's go back and drop it a little deeper and look during the daytime. What we see during the day is our landscapes. This is part of the Amazon Basin, a place called Rondônia in the south-center part of the Brazilian Amazon. If you look really carefully in the upper right-hand corner, you're going to see a thin white line, which is a road that was built in the 1970s. If we come back to the same place in 2001, what we're going to find is that these roads spurt off more roads, and more roads after that, at the end of which is a small clearing in the rainforest where there are going to be a few cows. These cows are used for beef. We're going to eat these cows. And these cows are eaten basically in South America, in Brazil and Argentina. They're not being shipped up here. But this kind of fishbone pattern of deforestation is something we notice a lot of around the tropics, especially in this part of the world. If we go a little bit further south in our little tour of the world, we can go to the Bolivian edge of the Amazon, here also in 1975, and if you look really carefully, there's a thin white line through that kind of seam, and there's a lone farmer out there in the middle of the primeval jungle. Let's come back again a few years later, here in 2003, and we'll see that that landscape actually looks a lot more like Iowa than it does like a rainforest. In fact, what you're seeing here are soybean fields. These soybeans are being shipped to Europe and to China as animal feed, especially after the mad cow disease scare about a decade ago, where we don't want to feed animals animal protein anymore, because that can transmit disease. Instead, we want to feed them more vegetable proteins. So soybeans have really exploded, showing how trade and globalization are really responsible for the connections to rainforests and the Amazon -- an incredibly strange and interconnected world that we have today. Well, again and again, what we find as we look around the world in our little tour of the world is that landscape after landscape after landscape have been cleared and altered for growing food and other crops. So one of the questions we've been asking is, how much of the world is used to grow food, and where is it exactly, and how can we change that into the future, and what does it mean? Well, our team has been looking at this on a global scale, using satellite data and ground-based data kind of to track farming on a global scale. And this is what we found, and it's startling. This map shows the presence of agriculture on planet Earth. The green areas are the areas we use to grow crops, like wheat or soybeans or corn or rice or whatever. That's 16 million square kilometers' worth of land. If you put it all together in one place, it'd be the size of South America. The second area, in brown, is the world's pastures and rangelands, where our animals live. That area's about 30 million square kilometers, or about an Africa's worth of land, a huge amount of land, and it's the best land, of course, is what you see. And what's left is, like, the middle of the Sahara Desert, or Siberia, or the middle of a rain forest. We're using a planet's worth of land already. If we look at this carefully, we find it's about 40 percent of the Earth's land surface is devoted to agriculture, and it's 60 times larger than all the areas we complain about, our suburban sprawl and our cities where we mostly live. Half of humanity lives in cities today, but a 60-times-larger area is used to grow food. So this is an amazing kind of result, and it really shocked us when we looked at that. So we're using an enormous amount of land for agriculture, but also we're using a lot of water. This is a photograph flying into Arizona, and when you look at it, you're like, "What are they growing here?" It turns out they're growing lettuce in the middle of the desert using water sprayed on top. Now, the irony is, it's probably sold in our supermarket shelves in the Twin Cities. But what's really interesting is, this water's got to come from some place, and it comes from here, the Colorado River in North America. Well, the Colorado on a typical day in the 1950s, this is just, you know, not a flood, not a drought, kind of an average day, it looks something like this. But if we come back today, during a normal condition to the exact same location, this is what's left. The difference is mainly irrigating the desert for food, or maybe golf courses in Scottsdale, you take your pick. Well, this is a lot of water, and again, we're mining water and using it to grow food, and today, if you travel down further down the Colorado, it dries up completely and no longer flows into the ocean. We've literally consumed an entire river in North America for irrigation. Well, that's not even the worst example in the world. This probably is: the Aral Sea. Now, a lot you will remember this from your geography classes. This is in the former Soviet Union in between Kazakhstan and Uzbekistan, one of the great inland seas of the world. But there's kind of a paradox here, because it looks like it's surrounded by desert. Why is this sea here? The reason it's here is because, on the right-hand side, you see two little rivers kind of coming down through the sand, feeding this basin with water. Those rivers are draining snowmelt from mountains far to the east, where snow melts, it travels down the river through the desert, and forms the great Aral Sea. Well, in the 1950s, the Soviets decided to divert that water to irrigate the desert to grow cotton, believe it or not, in Kazakhstan, to sell cotton to the international markets to bring foreign currency into the Soviet Union. They really needed the money. Well, you can imagine what happens. You turn off the water supply to the Aral Sea, what's going to happen? Here it is in 1973, 1986, 1999, 2004, and about 11 months ago. It's pretty extraordinary. Now a lot of us in the audience here live in the Midwest. Imagine that was Lake Superior. Imagine that was Lake Huron. It's an extraordinary change. This is not only a change in water and where the shoreline is, this is a change in the fundamentals of the environment of this region. Let's start with this. The Soviet Union didn't really have a Sierra Club. Let's put it that way. So what you find in the bottom of the Aral Sea ain't pretty. There's a lot of toxic waste, a lot of things that were dumped there that are now becoming airborne. One of those small islands that was remote and impossible to get to was a site of Soviet biological weapons testing. You can walk there today. Weather patterns have changed. Nineteen of the unique 20 fish species found only in the Aral Sea are now wiped off the face of the Earth. This is an environmental disaster writ large. But let's bring it home. This is a picture that Al Gore gave me a few years ago that he took when he was in the Soviet Union a long, long time ago, showing the fishing fleets of the Aral Sea. You see the canal they dug? They were so desperate to try to, kind of, float the boats into the remaining pools of water, but they finally had to give up because the piers and the moorings simply couldn't keep up with the retreating shoreline. I don't know about you, but I'm terrified that future archaeologists will dig this up and write stories about our time in history, and wonder, "What were you thinking?" Well, that's the future we have to look forward to. We already use about 50 percent of the Earth's fresh water that's sustainable, and agriculture alone is 70 percent of that. So we use a lot of water, a lot of land for agriculture. We also use a lot of the atmosphere for agriculture. Usually when we think about the atmosphere, we think about climate change and greenhouse gases, and mostly around energy, but it turns out agriculture is one of the biggest emitters of greenhouse gases too. If you look at carbon dioxide from burning tropical rainforest, or methane coming from cows and rice, or nitrous oxide from too many fertilizers, it turns out agriculture is 30 percent of the greenhouse
Esta noche quiero tener una conversación sobre este increíble tema global de la intersección entre el uso de la tierra, la comida y el ambiente, algo a lo que todos podemos relacionarnos y que he estado llamando, la otra verdad incómoda. Pero primero quiero llevarlos a un pequeño viaje. Visitemos primero nuestro planeta, pero de noche, y desde el espacio. Así luce nuestro planeta desde el espacio exterior a medianoche, si pudieran tomar un satélite y viajar alrededor del planeta. Y lo primero que notarán, claro, es qué tan dominante es la presencia humana en nuestro planeta. Vemos ciudades, campos de petróleo, incluso distinguimos la flotas pesqueras en el mar, que dominamos gran parte del planeta, y principalmente mediante el uso de energía que podemos ver aquí de noche. Pero retrocedamos y bajemos un poco más profundo y miremos durante el día. Lo que vemos es nuestros paisajes. Esto es parte de la cuenca amazónica, un lugar llamado Rondônia en la parte central sur de la amazonia brasileña. Si ven con cuidado en la esquina superior derecha verán una delgada línea blanca, que es un camino construido en los 70. Si volvemos al mismo sitio en 2001 encontraremos que estos caminos se desplegaron en más caminos, y más después, al final de los cuales hay un pequeño claro en el bosque donde habrá algunas vacas. Estas vacas se usan para carne. Vamos a comérnoslas. Y se comerán básicamente en Suramérica, en Brasil y Argentina. No serán enviadas aquí. Pero este patrón de espina de pescado de desforestación lo vemos con frecuencia alrededor de los trópicos especialmente en esta parte del mundo. Si vamos un poco al sur en nuestro pequeño viaje podemos ir a la parte boliviana del Amazonas, aquí aún en 1975, y si vemos con cuidado, hay un delgada línea blanca como de costura y un solitario granjero en medio de la selva primaveral. Volvamos otra vez, unos pocos años atrás, en 2003 y veremos cómo realmente luce más como Iowa que como un bosque húmedo. De hecho, lo que vemos son campos de soya. Esta soya se enviará a Europa y China, como forraje, especialmente después de la enfermedad de las vacas locas cerca de una década atrás, cuando decidimos no alimentar más a los animales con proteína animal, porque podía transmitir la enfermedad. En cambio, quisimos darles más proteína vegetal. Así que la soya realmente explotó mostrando qué tanto realmente responden el comercio y la globalización por la desforestación de la selva tropical húmeda y la amazonia, un extrañamente increíble e interconectado mundo que tenemos hoy. Bien, una y otra vez, lo que vemos si miramos alrededor del mundo en nuestro pequeño viaje es que los paisajes, uno tras otro, han sido despejados y alterados para sembrar comida y otros cultivos. Así que una de las preguntas que nos hacemos es, ¿qué tanto del mundo se usa para cultivar comida dónde exactamente, y qué tanto cambiará esto en el futuro, y qué implicará? Nuestro grupo ha estado mirando esto a escala global usando datos satelitales y datos de campo de seguimiento de la agricultura a escala global. Y esto es lo que hemos encontrado, y es sorprendente. Este mapa muestra la presencia de la agricultura en el planeta Tierra. Las áreas verdes son las que usamos para cultivos como trigo, soya, maíz, arroz o lo que sea. Son 16 millones de km² de tierra. Si los pones en un lugar, equivalen al tamaño de Suramérica. La segunda área, marrón, son los pastos y dehesas donde viven nuestros animales. Es un área de 30 millones de km², o cerca de toda la tierra de África. una enorme cantidad de tierra, y es la mejor, claro, es lo que ven. Y lo que queda es, como la mitad del desierto del Sahara, o Siberia, o la mitad del bosque húmedo. Ya estamos usando la riqueza de tierra del planeta. Si miramos con cuidado, encontramos cerca del 40% de la superficie Tierra está dedicada a la agricultura, y es 60 veces mayor que toda el área que reclamamos para nuestra expansión suburbana y las ciudades en las que vivimos. Media humanidad vive en las ciudades hoy, pero un área 60 veces más grande se usa para cultivar alimentos. Esto es un resultado sorprendente y realmente nos afecta cuando los vemos. Así que no solo usamos una cantidad enorme de tierra para agricultura sino que también usamos una gran cantidad de agua. Esta es una foto aérea de Arizona y cuando la miras, es como: "¿Que cultivan aquí?" Resulta que cultivan lechuga en medio del desierto usando agua esparcida desde lo alto. La ironía es que, probablemente se vende en nuestros supermercados en Twin Cities. Pero lo realmente interesante es, de dónde viene el agua para este lugar, y viene de aquí, del río Colorado en Norteamérica. Bueno, el Colorado en un día típico en los 1950 era como, saben, ni una inundación, ni sequía, en promedio, lucía algo así. Pero si vamos hoy, en condición normal en exactamente la misma localización, lo que queda es esto. La diferencia es principalmente por irrigar cultivos en el desierto o de pronto campos de golf en Scottsdale, Uds. elijan. Bueno, es una gran cantidad de agua, y, otra vez, estamos haciendo minería de agua y usándola para cultivos de alimento, y hoy, si viajan más abajo del Colorado, está seco del todo y ya no llega al océano. estamos consumiendo, literalmente, todos los ríos de Norteamérica para irrigación. Bueno, no es el peor ejemplo del mundo. Este probablemente sí: el mar de Aral. Muchos de Uds. lo recordarán por sus clases de geografía. Esta es la antigua Unión Soviética entre Kazajistán y Uzbekistán, uno de los grandes mares interiores del mundo. Pero hay una especie de paradoja aquí, porque parece como si estuviera rodeado de desierto. ¿Por qué está el mar aquí? La razón de que esté aquí es que, en la parte derecha, ven dos pequeños ríos que bajan por la arena, alimentando esta cuenca con agua. Esos ríos están drenando nieve derretida de las montañas lejanas del este, donde la nieve se derrite, descienden por el río por el desierto, y forma el gran mar de Aral. Bien, en los 50, los soviéticos decidieron desviar esta agua para irrigar el desierto y cultivar algodón, créanlo o no, en Kazajstán, para vender algodón en los mercados internacionales y conseguir divisas para la Unión Soviética. Realmente necesitaban ese dinero. Bien, imaginarán lo que pasó. Si cierras la llave del agua del mar de Aral, ¿qué pasará? Aquí en 1973, 1986, 1999, y cerca de 11 meses atrás. Es bastante extraordinario. Ahora, muchos de Uds. viven en el medio oeste. Imaginen que fuera el lago Superior. Imaginen que fuera el lago Hurón. Este es un cambio extraordinario. Este no es solo un cambio en el agua y dónde queda la costa, es un cambio en los fundamentos del medio ambiente en esta región. Comencemos con esto. La Unión Soviética en realidad no tenía un Sierra Club. Pongámoslo así. Así que lo que encontramos en el fondo del mar de Aral no es agradable. Hay muchos residuos tóxicos, cantidad de cosas que fueron botadas ahí y que ahora empiezan a estar en el aire. Una de esas pequeñas islas que eran remotas e imposibles de llegar, fue sitio de prueba soviético de armas biológicas. Uno puede caminar allí hoy. Los patrones climáticos cambiaron. 19 de 20 especies únicas de peces que se encontraban solo en el mar de Aral desaparecieron de la faz de la Tierra. El desastre ambiental es muy evidente. Pero volvamos a casa. Esta es una foto que Al Gore me dio hace unos años que tomó cuando estuvo en la Unión Soviética mucho, mucho tiempo atrás, que muestra las flotas pesqueras en el mar de Aral. ¿Ven el canal que cavan? Estaban tan desesperados de tratar de que los botes flotaran en lo que quedaba de agua... pero finalmente tuvieron que rendirse porque los muelles y amarres simplemente no podían mantenerse al día con el litoral que se retiraba. No se Uds., pero me aterra que futuros arqueólogos caven esto y escriban historias de nuestro tiempo, y se pregunten, "¿En qué estaban pensando?" Bien, ese es el futuro que tenemos que afrontar. Ya estamos usando el 50% del agua dulce de la Tierra que es sostenible, y la sola agricultura es un 70% de eso. Así que usamos mucha agua, mucha tierra en agricultura. También usamos mucho de la atmósfera para la agricultura. Usualmente cuando pensamos en la atmósfera pensamos en cambio climático y gases de efecto invernadero y principalmente en energía, pero resulta que la agricultura es también uno de los mayores emisores de gases de efecto invernadero. Si miran el CO2 de la quema de selva húmeda tropical, o el metano de la vacas y el arroz, o el oxido nitroso de muchos fertilizantes, resulta que la agricultura aporta el 30% de los gases de efecto
gases going into the atmosphere from human activity. That's more than all our transportation. It's more than all our electricity. It's more than all other manufacturing, in fact. It's the single largest emitter of greenhouse gases of any human activity in the world. And yet, we don't talk about it very much. So we have this incredible presence today of agriculture dominating our planet, whether it's 40 percent of our land surface, 70 percent of the water we use, 30 percent of our greenhouse gas emissions. We've doubled the flows of nitrogen and phosphorus around the world simply by using fertilizers, causing huge problems of water quality from rivers, lakes, and even oceans, and it's also the single biggest driver of biodiversity loss. So without a doubt, agriculture is the single most powerful force unleashed on this planet since the end of the ice age. No question. And it rivals climate change in importance. And they're both happening at the same time. But what's really important here to remember is that it's not all bad. It's not that agriculture's a bad thing. In fact, we completely depend on it. It's not optional. It's not a luxury. It's an absolute necessity. We have to provide food and feed and, yeah, fiber and even biofuels to something like seven billion people in the world today, and if anything, we're going to have the demands on agriculture increase into the future. It's not going to go away. It's going to get a lot bigger, mainly because of growing population. We're seven billion people today heading towards at least nine, probably nine and a half before we're done. More importantly, changing diets. As the world becomes wealthier as well as more populous, we're seeing increases in dietary consumption of meat, which take a lot more resources than a vegetarian diet does. So more people, eating more stuff, and richer stuff, and of course having an energy crisis at the same time, where we have to replace oil with other energy sources that will ultimately have to include some kinds of biofuels and bio-energy sources. So you put these together. It's really hard to see how we're going to get to the rest of the century without at least doubling global agricultural production. Well, how are we going to do this? How are going to double global ag production around the world? Well, we could try to farm more land. This is an analysis we've done, where on the left is where the crops are today, on the right is where they could be based on soils and climate, assuming climate change doesn't disrupt too much of this, which is not a good assumption. We could farm more land, but the problem is the remaining lands are in sensitive areas. They have a lot of biodiversity, a lot of carbon, things we want to protect. So we could grow more food by expanding farmland, but we'd better not, because it's ecologically a very, very dangerous thing to do. Instead, we maybe want to freeze the footprint of agriculture and farm the lands we have better. This is work that we're doing to try to highlight places in the world where we could improve yields without harming the environment. The green areas here show where corn yields, just showing corn as an example, are already really high, probably the maximum you could find on Earth today for that climate and soil, but the brown areas and yellow areas are places where we're only getting maybe 20 or 30 percent of the yield you should be able to get. You see a lot of this in Africa, even Latin America, but interestingly, Eastern Europe, where Soviet Union and Eastern Bloc countries used to be, is still a mess agriculturally. Now, this would require nutrients and water. It's going to either be organic or conventional or some mix of the two to deliver that. Plants need water and nutrients. But we can do this, and there are opportunities to make this work. But we have to do it in a way that is sensitive to meeting the food security needs of the future and the environmental security needs of the future. We have to figure out how to make this tradeoff between growing food and having a healthy environment work better. Right now, it's kind of an all-or-nothing proposition. We can grow food in the background -- that's a soybean field — and in this flower diagram, it shows we grow a lot of food, but we don't have a lot clean water, we're not storing a lot of carbon, we don't have a lot of biodiversity. In the foreground, we have this prairie that's wonderful from the environmental side, but you can't eat anything. What's there to eat? We need to figure out how to bring both of those together into a new kind of agriculture that brings them all together. Now, when I talk about this, people often tell me, "Well, isn't blank the answer?" -- organic food, local food, GMOs, new trade subsidies, new farm bills -- and yeah, we have a lot of good ideas here, but not any one of these is a silver bullet. In fact, what I think they are is more like silver buckshot. And I love silver buckshot. You put it together and you've got something really powerful, but we need to put them together. So what we have to do, I think, is invent a new kind of agriculture that blends the best ideas of commercial agriculture and the green revolution with the best ideas of organic farming and local food and the best ideas of environmental conservation, not to have them fighting each other but to have them collaborating together to form a new kind of agriculture, something I call "terraculture," or farming for a whole planet. Now, having this conversation has been really hard, and we've been trying very hard to bring these key points to people to reduce the controversy, to increase the collaboration. I want to show you a short video that does kind of show our efforts right now to bring these sides together into a single conversation. So let me show you that. (Music) ("Institute on the Environment, University of Minnesota: Driven to Discover") ("The world population is growing by 75 million people each year. That's almost the size of Germany. Today, we're nearing 7 billion people. At this rate, we'll reach 9 billion people by 2040. And we all need food. But how? How do we feed a growing world without destroying the planet? We already know climate change is a big problem. But it's not the only problem. We need to face 'the other inconvenient truth.' A global crisis in agriculture. Population growth + meat consumption + dairy consumption + energy costs + bioenergy production = stress on natural resources. More than 40% of Earth's land has been cleared for agriculture. Global croplands cover 16 million km². That's almost the size of South America. Global pastures cover 30 million km². That's the size of Africa. Agriculture uses 60 times more land than urban and suburban areas combined. Irrigation is the biggest use of water on the planet. We use 2,800 cubic kilometers of water on crops every year. That's enough to fill 7,305 Empire State Buildings every day. Today, many large rivers have reduced flows. Some dry up altogether. Look at the Aral Sea, now turned to desert. Or the Colorado River, which no longer flows to the ocean. Fertilizers have more than doubled the phosphorus and nitrogen in the environment. The consequence? Widespread water pollution and massive degradation of lakes and rivers. Surprisingly, agriculture is the biggest contributor to climate change. It generates 30% of greenhouse gas emissions. That's more than the emissions from all electricity and industry, or from all the world's planes, trains and automobiles. Most agricultural emissions come from tropical deforestation, methane from animals and rice fields, and nitrous oxide from over-fertilizing. There is nothing we do that transforms the world more than agriculture. And there's nothing we do that is more crucial to our survival. Here's the dilemma... As the world grows by several billion more people, We'll need to double, maybe even triple, global food production. So where do we go from here? We need a bigger conversation, an international dialogue. We need to invest in real solutions: incentives for farmers, precision agriculture, new crop varieties, drip irrigation, gray water recycling, better tillage practices, smarter diets. We need everyone at the table. Advocates of commercial agriculture, environmental conservation, and organic farming... must work together. There is no single solution. We need collaboration, imagination, determination, because failure is not an option. How do we feed the world without destroying it? Yeah, so we face one of the greatest grand challenges in all of human history today: the need to feed nine billion people and do so sustainably and equitably and justly, at the same time protecting our planet for this and future generations. This is going to be one of the hardest things we ever have done in human history, and we absolutely have to get it right, and we have to get it right on our first and only try. So thanks very much. (Applause)
invernadero que van a la atmósfera por actividad humana. Esto es más que todos nuestros transportes. Es más que toda nuestra electricidad. Es más que toda la otra manufactura, de hecho. Es el principal emisor individual de gases de efecto invernadero de cualquier actividad humana en el mundo. Y sin embargo, no hablamos mucho de ello. Así que tenemos esta increíble presencia de agricultura hoy, dominando nuestro planeta que viene siendo el 40% de la superficie de tierra, el 70% de uso de agua, el 30% de la emisión de gases con efecto invernadero Hemos duplicado el flujo de nitrógeno y fosfatos alrededor del mundo solo por usar fertilizantes, causando grandes problemas de calidad de agua en los ríos, lagos y hasta océanos, y es también la mayor causa de pérdida de biodiversidad. Así que sin duda la agricultura es la fuerza más poderosa desatada en este planeta desde la edad del hielo. Sin duda. Y rivaliza con el cambio climático en importancia. Y los dos están sucediendo al mismo tiempo. Pero lo importante para recordar es que no todo es malo. No es que la agricultura sea una cosa mala. De hecho, dependemos completamente de ella. No es opcional. No es un lujo. Es absolutamente necesaria. Necesitamos proveer comida y pienso y, sí, fibras e incluso biocombustibles para algo así como 7 mil millones de personas en el mundo hoy, y si pasa algo, es que esas demandas a la agricultura aumentarán en el futuro. No va a desaparecer. Va a ser aún mayor, principalmente por el aumento de la población. Somos 7 mil millones hoy llegando al menos a 9, probablemente nueve y medio hasta parar. Más importante, con cambio de dieta. Conforme el mundo se vuelve más sano y más populoso, aumentamos nuestro consumo de carne, lo que consume más recursos que la comida vegetariana. Así que más personas, comen más y con más abundancia y claro, con una crisis energética al mismo tiempo por la que tenemos que reemplazar petróleo por otras fuentes lo que en última instancia tendrá que incluir más biocombustibles y fuentes de bioenergía. Así que pongan todo junto. Es realmente duro ver cómo vamos a lograrlo para el resto del siglo sin doblar al menos la producción agrícola global. Bien, ¿cómo vamos a hacerlo? ¿Cómo vamos a doblar la agricultura global en el mundo? Bueno, podemos cultivar más tierra. Este es el análisis que hicimos, en la izquierda es donde hay cultivos hoy, en la derecha donde los debería haber, basados en suelos y clima, suponiendo que el cambio climático no haga mucho daño a esto, que no es una buena presunción. Podemos cultivar más tierra, pero el problema es que las tierras restantes son áreas sensibles. Tienen mucha diversidad, mucho carbono, cosas que queremos proteger. Así que podemos cultivar más expandiendo las tierras de labrantío pero es mejor no hacerlo, porque ecológicamente es muy, muy peligroso hacerlo. En cambio, quizá queramos congelar la huella de la agricultura y trabajar mejor las tierras que tenemos. Este es trabajo que estamos haciendo para resaltar los lugares en el mundo donde podemos mejorar los rendimientos sin dañar el medioambiente. Las áreas verdes aquí muestran dónde se da el maíz, solo muestra el maíz como ejemplo, ya es muy alta, probablemente lo máximo que se puede encontrar en la Tierra hoy para este clima y suelo, pero las áreas marrones y amarillas, son lugares donde solo hay un 20 o 30% del rendimiento que se podría lograr. Ven muchas en África, incluso en Latinoamérica, pero noten que en Europa del este, donde la Unión Soviética y los países del Bloque del este estaban, la agricultura es todavía un desastre. Ahora, esto requiere nutrientes y agua. Será u orgánica o convencional o alguna mezcla de las dos. Las plantas necesitan agua y nutrientes. Pero podemos hacerlo y hay oportunidades para hacer este trabajo. Pero tenemos que hacerlo de forma que sea sensible para cubrir la seguridad de alimentos del futuro y la seguridad medio ambiental necesaria en el futuro. Tenemos que ver cómo hacemos esta compensacón entre cultivar comida y tener un ambiente sano, que funcione mejor. Ahora mismo, es una especie de 'todo o nada'. Podemos cultivar comida en el fondo —este es un campo de soya— y en este diagrama de flor, se muestra que cultivamos mucha comida pero no tenemos mucha agua limpia, no reservamos mucho carbono, no tenemos mucha biodiversidad. En primer plano, tenemos esta pradera magnífica desde el punto de vista ambiental, pero no puedes comer nada. ¿Qué hay para comer? Tenemos que ingeniarnos la forma de unirlas en un nuevo tipo de agricultura que nos dé ambas cosas. Ahora, cuando hablo de esto, la gente con frecuencia me dice: "Bien, ¿no es obvia la respuesta? Comida orgánica, comida local, organismos modificados genéticamente, nuevos subsidios al comercio y a las granjas". Y sí, tenemos cantidades de buenas ideas, pero ninguna es una varita mágica. De hecho, lo que creo es que hay más como trucos mágicos. Y adoro los trucos. Los pones juntos y obtienes algo de verdad poderoso, pero necesitamos ponerlos juntos. Así que lo que tenemos que hacer, creo, es inventar una nueva forma de agricultura que mezcle las mejores ideas de la agricultura comercial y la revolución verde con las mejores ideas de la agricultura orgánica y la comida local y las mejores ideas de conservación del ambiente, no tenerlos luchando uno con otro, sino tenerlos colaborando juntos en una nueva forma de agricultura, algo que llamo "terracultura" o cultivo para todo el planeta. Ahora, tener esta conversación es de verdad duro y nosotros hemos intentado con ahínco traer estos puntos claves a la gente para reducir la controversia y aumentar la colaboración. Quiero mostrarles un video corto que trata de mostrar el tipo de esfuerzos que estamos haciendo para unir estos lados en una única conversación. Déjenme mostrárselos. (Música) ("Instituto de Medioambiente, Universidad de Minnesota: Guiando el descubrimiento) ("La población mundial crece 75 millones de personas cada año. Esto es casi la población de Alemania. Hoy somos cerca de 7 mil millones de personas. A este paso, seremos 9 mil millones para el 2040. Y todos necesitamos comida. ¿Pero qué? ¿Cómo podemos alimentar al mundo sin destruir el planeta? Ya sabemos que el cambio climático es un gran problema. Pero no es el único problema. Necesitamos enfrentar 'la otra verdad incómoda'. Una crisis global en la agricultura. Aumento de la población + consumo de carne + consumo de leche + costos energéticos + producción de bioenergía = estrés de los recursos naturales. Más del 40% de los suelos de la Tierra se han despejado para agricultura. Los cultivos globales cubren 16 millones de km². Esto es casi el tamaño de Suramérica. Los pastizales globales cubren 30 millones de km². Es el tamaño de África. La agricultura usa 60 veces más tierra que las áreas urbanas y suburbanas combinadas. La irrigación es el mayor uso del agua del planeta. Usamos 2 000 kilómetros cúbicos de agua en cultivos cada año. Es tanto como llenar 7 305 Empire States cada día. Hoy, muchos grandes ríos están reducidos a arroyos. Algunos se secaron del todo. Miren el mar de Aral, ahora un desierto. O el río Colorado, que ya no llega al océano. Los fertilizantes han más que duplicado los fosfatos y el nitrógeno del ambiente. ¿La consecuencia? Polución generalizada del agua y degradación masiva de lagos y ríos. Sorprendentemente, la agricultura es el mayor contribuyente del cambio climático. Genera el 30% de los gases de efecto invernadero. Es más que la emisión de toda la electricidad y la industria de todos los aviones, trenes y automóviles del mundo. Muchas emisiones por agricultura vienen de la desforestación tropical, el metano de los animales y los campos de arroz, el oxido nitroso de la fertilización alta. No hay nada que hayamos hecho que transforme más al mundo que la agricultura. Y nada es más crucial para nuestra sobrevivencia. Este es el dilema... Conforme el mundo crece en varios miles de millones de personas, necesitamos duplicar, quizá triplicar, la producción global de comida. Así que, ¿a dónde vamos? Necesitamos una gran conversación, un diálogo internacional. Necesitamos invertir en soluciones reales: incentivos para agricultores, agricultura de precisión, nuevas variedades de cultivos, irrigación por goteo, reciclar aguas negras, mejores prácticas de labranza, dietas inteligentes. Necesitamos a todos en la mesa. Defensores de la agricultura comercial, ambientalistas, granjeros orgánicos... necesitamos trabajar juntos. No hay una única solución. Necesitamos colaboración, imaginación, determinación, porque fallar no es una opción. ¿Cómo alimentamos el mundo sin destruirlo?") Sí, enfrentamos uno de los mayores retos de toda la historia de la humanidad: necesitamos alimentar 9 mil millones de personas y hacerlo de forma sostenible, equitativa y justa, a la vez que protegemos nuestro planeta para esta y las siguientes generaciones. Esta será una de las cosas más difíciles que haya hecho la humanidad en su historia y tenemos que hacerlo muy bien, y hacerlo bien en nuestro primer y quizá único intento. Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)